<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fruitful sermon necessary for the time preached at the Spittle vpon the Tuesday in Easter weeke last, by Frauncis Marbury. Published by direction of authoritie.</title>
            <author>Marbury, Francis, d. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06872</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847254</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12281</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248548605</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17305</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S111995</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847254e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 812:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fruitful sermon necessary for the time preached at the Spittle vpon the Tuesday in Easter weeke last, by Frauncis Marbury. Published by direction of authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Marbury, Francis, d. 1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[86] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By P. Short, dwelling on Breadstreet hill at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴ (-F4).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the Spittle on Easter Tuesdaie, 1602.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:1"/>
            <p>A FRVITFVL SERMON NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SARY FOR THE TIME, preached at the Spittle vpon <hi>the Tuesday in Easter weeke</hi> last, by <hi>Frauncis Marbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Published by direction of Authoritie.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>P. Short,</hi> dwelling <hi>on Breadstreet hill at the signe of the</hi> Starre, 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethren, when I saw how Satan had preuailed by his latter temptations, to adde a further miserie to those e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils which he had contriued by his former: I desired that by some good hand he might be resisted. And for a good space (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) I haue inclined to aduenture my selfe in opposing him. I foresaw how vnacceptable it would be to some, and reuolued it with such anxietie of minde, as I could not remooue by mine own strength. But it was the Lords worke that I set aside discouragements, and fell to waighing the matter. Three things I principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pondred. First, that this vndutifull alienation did grieuously displease God, and was a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous iudgement of it selfe. Secondly, that it had no ground but the <hi>tradition of Satan;</hi> so I call the information which is giuen to men, that are strangers to the secrets of a cause, by those that are parties to the action Thirdly, that the effect of this alienation, if it were too much inueterat would be formidable to all, and chiefly to gods Church. Hereupon I resolued to wait some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to performe this duty, and to endure mine owne losse for the gaine of others. In this corruption of nature it is not possible to do any thing exactly wel, and by that verie thing doth the Lord aduantage his glorie: for so he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth
<pb facs="tcp:12281:3"/>the instruments of the best things. How beit he giueth grace to his children to attaine to vndoubted synceritie, and to propound his glory to their enterprises in the singlenesse of their harts. The falsenesse of mans hart (if he set himselfe seriously before God) cannot so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, but he may discerne whether he haue had a care to auoid euil and to glorifie God. In this care I haue had my part from my first cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to preach at the Spittle. And if men wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me otherwise,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.36.</note>
               <hi>my conscience will make her a garland of their reports,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> saith. I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that after I was called to that place, I thought my selfe qualified in some measure for this very purpose, vpon these grounds, 1. I stood well affected to my countrimen, whom I desired to reforme. 2. I presumed that they had entertained a perswasion that I affected soundnesse in deliuering Gods word. 3. I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the cause with the distinctions. 4. I vnderstood out of my innumerable obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the still continuing dispositions and words of men in the cause, to be verie sinfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, notwithstanding all their distinctions. And I proportioned the reprehensiō of an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall sin to an vniuersall assembly. 5. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that the wound being cured betweene God and man, and between man and man, we should all be fit to ioine against the Diuell, and leaue failing both in dutifulnes and wisedome.</p>
            <p>I haue (being required thereto) deliuered a faithfull report of that Sermon. I haue not (the
<pb facs="tcp:12281:3"/>Lord is witnesse) set downe one word to diuert y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sense of any one point frō that which I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the deliuerie, but haue striuen to attaine to the words. My conscience is vpright so farre as I can discerne it in the course. If the great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of state had called me to preach before them, I would either haue insisted in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the common duties of christianitie, or els would haue held it my duty to haue left this, and to haue followed the other relatiue. To haue done it now, had been preposterous.</p>
            <p>As touching <hi>politike vertues,</hi> which I holde <hi>more excellent for the profit of the commonwealth in true christian princes, then their morall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues be;</hi> doe me right in vnderstanding me as I expressely spake it, and as I wrote it (vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion) more then once before, I spake it <hi>of true christian princes.</hi> Otherwise I hold a <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in his defectiuenesse of policie (if he be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise truly religious) a fitter king thē a <hi>Ieroboam</hi> being an enemy of religion, with all his irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious policies. Conceiue also the largenes of the name of politike vertues,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that in deed it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth in the scripture phrase (which I thoght of) to a mans carriage in common with others be he priuate or publike;<note place="margin">Act. 23.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Reg. 8.23. 2. cro. 20 6. Psal. 42.4 &amp; 122.</note> insomuch that <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth his conscionable seruice of God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersing amongst the Iewes <hi>his politike carriage.</hi> And therfore in princes it extendeth to all their duties, as they bee princes, euen to their verie praiers as they are the mouths of their people, as it sometimes fell out, and to their resorting
<pb facs="tcp:12281:4"/>to the publike worship of God as guides to the people, these are politike duties, as they are don in a politike respect for gouernments sake, for the name of policie is abusiuely put for vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable craftinesse.</p>
            <p>If there were any ambitious intention in me,<note place="margin">1 Thess. 4.11.</note> it was <hi>S. Pauls</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I was ambitious of loue and quietnesse in my countrey. Other sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises are vaine; for though I desire to exercise my ministerie with the ayde and countenance of authoritie for the repulsing of vngodly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, yet I may affirm with all truth of hart that I haue as much mind to turn my endeuors from the painful preaching of the Gospel to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, as <hi>Barzillai</hi> had to be a Courtier. Wel,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.35.</note> the Lord enforme you all with all profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and conuenient truth, and frame your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections thereafter. And the Lord giue vs all grace to turne all our vnnecessarie medlings with Counsels and States, to prayers &amp; thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings for our blessed Lady Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:4"/>
            <head>The Dialogue betweene <hi>Salomon</hi> and his Subiect.</head>
            <head>
               <bibl>Eccles. 10.4.</bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label>Salomon.</label>
               <hi>4.</hi> IF the spirit of him that is in authority rise vp against thee, leaue not thy place. For gentlenesse pacifieth great sinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Subject.</label>
               <hi>5.</hi> There is an euill, that I haue seene vnder the sunne, as an error that proceedeth from the face of him that ruleth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>6.</hi> Folly is set in great excellencie, and the rich is set in low place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>7.</hi> I haue seene seruants on horses, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces walking as seruants on the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Salomon.</label>
               <hi>8.</hi> He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it, and he that breaketh an hedge, a Serpent hall bite him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>9.</hi> He that remooueth stones, shall hurt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb facs="tcp:12281:5"/>thereby, and he that cutteth wood, shall be in danger thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>10.</hi> If the iron he blunt, and one hath not whet the edge, he must then put to more strength, but the excellencie of a thing is wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>11.</hi> If the Serpent bite when he is not char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, no better is a babler.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>12.</hi> The wordes of the lippes of a wise man haue grace: but the lippes of a foole deuoure himselfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>13.</hi> The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishnesse and the latter end of his mouth is wicked madnesse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>14.</hi> For the foole multiplieth wordes: yet the man knoweth not what shall be, and who can tell him what shall be after him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>15.</hi> The labour of the foole doth wearie him, yet he knoweth not to go into the Citie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Subject.</label>
               <hi>16.</hi> Wo to thee O Land, when thy King is a childe, and thy Princes eate in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>17.</hi> Blessed art thou O Land, when thy King is the sonne of Nobles, and thy Princes eate
<pb facs="tcp:12281:5"/>in time for strength, and not for drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>18.</hi> By slothfulnesse the roofe of the house goeth to decay, and by idlenesse of the hands the house droppeth thorough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>19.</hi> They prepare bread for laughter, and wine comforteth the liuing, and siluer go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for all.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Salomon.</label>
               <hi>20.</hi> Curse not the King, no not in thy thought; nor the rich, no not in thy bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eccles. 10. verse 20.</bibl>
                  <p>Curse not the king, no not in thy though; neither curse the rich, no not in thy bed-chamber; for the foule of the heauen shall carrie the voice, and that which hath winges shall declare the matter.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke being made after <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> rising from his fall, hath the commendation both of his repentance and of the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his very soule, according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue title of precheresse (as one would saie giuen by himselfe) in the feminine gender.<note place="margin">Coheleth</note> It containeth a cōfession of the vanity of al mans priuate attempts in the 7. first chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: the 8. chap. mentioneth the vanity &amp; corruptiō of publick administrations with the scandale therof: the 9. mentioneth the ignorance &amp; mistaking of the diuine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations, togither with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vniust scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale therof. Now correspondently this 10. chap. containeth the cure of the first scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale as the 11. doth of the second.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</note>The principall question of this chap. be ginning it (<note n="a" place="margin">Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mellius.</note> with some) at the fourth verse is, that subiects that are godly wise, ought to represse in themselues al insurrection of mind, against the supposed scandales of ciuill administrations, and against the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of princes, and that a disloyal thought ought not to bee lent thereunto.</p>
            <p>The discourse wherof is propounded (as it were) dialogue wise betweene <hi>Salomon</hi> &amp; his subiect: <hi>Salomō</hi> beginneth this graue counsell of moderating the affections in the 4. verse. And the Subiect aunswereth slaunderously in the three next, insinuating that it is impossible to stand contented and of an appeased mind in a gouernment which hee surmiseth to be so scandalous, that it peruerteth and inuerteth the vse of preferments &amp; abasements. Thus out of his mere conceit he aymeth (possiblie) at some thing don by <hi>Salomon</hi> in his vxoriousnes, at the instigation of his Idolatrous wiues; yet without any ground for this cauil.</p>
            <p>The replie which <hi>Salomon</hi> returned to
<pb facs="tcp:12281:7"/>this obiection, is contained in the next 8. verses: The summe of the reply is, that it is daungerous folly for a subiect to beat his braines about these matters.</p>
            <p>The particulars are first 4. comparisons, to note out the peril, and a fift compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to note the irreuocablenes of the peril when men haue gon too far. The first cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison in the 8. verse is against curious ransackers of state matters, to dig vp scan dales to themselues and others, that they are like those that dig a pit and fall into it. The second comparison in the same verse is against those which incōsideratly rush against the priuiledges of old receiued by prescription, and scan the prerogatiue of their soueraign: which are likned to brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers vp of old hedges, where serpents lurke and bite them. The third compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son vers. 9. is against those which attempt to disioine the vnited body of a state by shooting at some particulars members of the same, who are likned to a remouer of stones that are cōpact in a building, &amp; so bringeth all vpon his head. The 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison, in the same verse and in the tenth
<pb facs="tcp:12281:8"/>is against those which think to right mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by violence, who are likened to those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thinke to cleaue knotty logs with blunt axes, &amp; so bruise themselues with violent rebounding blowes, &amp; yet cleaue not the logs; whereas the excellencie of a thing (in deed) is wisedome, that is, the excellēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est maner of walking to compasse a good matter is by the meekenes &amp; gratiousnes of wisedome, and not by violence. The fift comparison which is vers. 11. is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain men by terror from proceeding too far, because then their hurt wilbe incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whatsoeuer they alledge for thēselues for charming is but babling after that the serpent hath already bitten, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> harme should go before.</p>
            <p>Whereupon <hi>Salomon</hi> condudeth with a discourse of the tongue, tending to an exhortation to temper it wisely, by an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument taken from the contrarie effects of the contrary gouernment of the same, ver. 12. to wit either grace or destruction: and hee prosecuteth the euill effects: first describing the issue of busie talke.
<pb facs="tcp:12281:8"/>It beginneth (saith hee) at foolishnesse, and by reason of an vnbridled affection prooueth at the last wicked madnesse, verse 13. Secondly, the issue of foolish talke for want of graue premeditation, that a man cannot tell what wordes shall escape him, nor any body els neither, by that time hee hath made an end of his vnprepared colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for so soundeth the originall, verse 14. And thirdly, the issue of foolish med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by reason of ignorance, when men tire themselues with controuling of state mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; yet are many times so ignorant that they cannot manage their owne affaires, but are more like to them that know not to goe to the city though it bee a beaten way, nor can scarse tell the way home to their owne houses, verse 15. And thus farre the reply of <hi>Salomon.</hi> The subiect though conuinced, yet not resting in this counsel, verse 16. continueth his obiection as it were by way of reioinder, but now indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, and falleth to lamenting, that is, to cunning deprauing the state of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:12281:9"/>for the riotousnes &amp; dissolutenesse of the gouernors, &amp; verse 17. by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison preferreth the gouerment of other countreyes, and vers. the 18. and 19. taketh vpon him to prophesie euill to his owne, by comparing it with the priuate state of an vnthrift, who letteth all his things to go to decay by retchlesnesse, and consumeth himselfe with prodigality (so hee closely girdeth at the sumptuousnes of <hi>Salomon</hi>) presuming that a good purse will hold out and pay for all, til he haue nothing left.</p>
            <p>To this second obiection followeth now in this verse the surreioinder of <hi>Salomon,</hi> wherin yet he vouchsafeth not to way outa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny special answer to these busie particulars (for subiects must giue account to princes, and not princes to their subiects) but set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out an answere by hand, and generally that they were best to take heed of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of princes least they smarted for it.</p>
            <p>And this is the vniuersall context which I thought expedient to go about to cleere, because the coherence of the Hebrue stile
<pb facs="tcp:12281:9"/>is not so much relieued to the vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the most with helpes of inference to connect or to distinguish the parts, as the Greeke is. And I desired to make the desending out of the contexte into the text to be of easie passage and sensible.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of the text.</note>The text it selfe hath two generall parts which lay open themselues: an exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and an argument. The exhortation hath likewise two, and the argument as many. The first part of the exhortation is, not to depraue the King, for the word signifieth so much as to make light account of. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the exhortation is, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue the Rich, vnderstanding the word rich not literally only, but metaphorically also, for persons of worth, qualified with vertues &amp; parts, such as kings do or should principallie imploy in their affaires: which signification of the word is pregnantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of the sixt verse of this chapter. And this name is giuen them here of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, because men of so great imployment are commonly inriched, and their riches
<pb facs="tcp:12281:10"/>become an eye sore to many. This (as I haue said) is deliuered by way of for bidding vnder the forme of an exhortation, &amp; not an austere commandement, which affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth a soft hart more, howbeit the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings be not both of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same value: for that which cōcerneth the king is more absolute as a prohibition, and that concerning the rich is lesse absolute as an inhibition. This appeareth by the seuerall extents of these two forbiddings; for the kinge may not be depraued <hi>no not in thy thought,</hi> &amp; the rich may not be depraued <hi>no not in thy bedchā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the withdrawing of thy bedchā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. For the reuerence of the kinge God hath immediatly seated vpon the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the subiect. And the subordinate Magistrate is seated on the conscience to, but mediatly according to the authority giuen hym by the king; so that he so far sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vppon the conscience as he is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the King, and is more easily diuided by his particular offences, when he abuseth his prince &amp; his authority. Against whom
<pb facs="tcp:12281:10"/>neuerthelesse a good subiest cannot irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly mutter with a good conscience, nor depraue him in corners, though hee doe giue cause to be euill thought of. Thus the deprauation of either is seuerallie forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with this difference, but in one and the same verbe, &amp; that in such a grauitie therof as importeth the effect of such malignitie, which for the most part redoundeth to some violation or hurt of the gouernours. And the word <hi>Gam</hi> (rightly valued in the translatiō to no not) is added to the first for vehemencie, &amp; must also be vnderstood, &amp; so supplied to the latter for the same cause.</p>
            <p>The argument by an inuerted order fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Hebrewes, first speaketh of the danger of deprauing of the rich. And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of the danger of deprauing the king both hyperbolically: <hi>that birds shal detect it,</hi> to signifie that men can haue no security by committing this sin intestate. The danger of deprauing the rich, is that the voice of whisperers against them shalbe carried by the foule of the heauē, and the danger of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauing
<pb facs="tcp:12281:11"/>of the king is, that the ill matter conceiued against him in the minde what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer it be (for <hi>Dabhar</hi> is answereable to <hi>Res,</hi> &amp; signifieth any thing) though not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, shalbe declared not by any ordinary foule of the heauen as the former, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the maister of winges after the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braisme, that is, by the swiftest foule. For the prouidence of God vseth speciall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in detecting the iniuries intended or conceiued against the supreame magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate.</p>
            <p>As if <hi>Salomon</hi> had propoūded to his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the same matter in more wordes thus.<note place="margin">The para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase.</note> I see well that counsel is good to those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> are good: but as for thee thou hast the fault of an euil seruant that is answeringe againe: thou hast thy part in those foolish allegations, that thought is free, &amp; that a cat may looke on a King. One while thou bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest princes for misdisposing of honors: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother while thou carpest at them &amp; the magistrates vnder them for dissolutenesse &amp; ryot. What should I say to thee? should
<pb facs="tcp:12281:11"/>I make account to thee? thou art no fit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor of these reckonings. Take heed to thy selfe and to thy spirit: thou art surely in the way of Atheists and hypocrites: for theirs is the spirit of malignity: and to the first borne of them doth slaunder belong in this high nature. I exhort thee therfore to keep both a good tongue and a good heart with thee, &amp; in entring into kings matters to lay aside first pride, which puffeth vp. Secondly superfluity of folly, which distasteth wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it selfe. Thirdly, want of compassion, which rashly condemneth that which wise charity would tolerate. Fourthly, lack of equitie, which layeth imputations crosse. And fiftly, vnthankfulnesse for the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings by and from princes. Do thou not depraue the King no not in the whispe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of thy consciēce. Make not thy heart a den of surmises. And as touching those principal magistrates against whom vnder colour of lamentation thou makest such an outcrye: giue not thy selfe leaue to depraue them, no not when thou hast remoued all
<pb facs="tcp:12281:12"/>witnesses in thy most retyred closet. Enuie not their riches. Traduce not their seueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Condemne not their policy. Be not rash in any of these thinges. Throw all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice out of thy conscience, and place reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to authority in the roome. Leaue curious prying and credulousnesse to the right owners: I meane busie bodies. He which made the conscience and hath assig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned authoritie a place there, hath a quicke ear, &amp; by his prouidence returneth a speedy intelligence of these faults, as worthie so high a detector. For what is spoken against magistrates, the birds of the aire shall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie tidinges of it. And whatsoeuer is but in hart spoken against the king himselfe, God will make out the maister of the winges a most speedy accuser to declare the matter; rather then faile hee will afford a miracle. Of a truth the vengeance of God will find out such a sinner, and when hee is founde out, the holy ghost as well as the king will be his enemie.</p>
            <p>The holy ghost out of this text thus to
<pb facs="tcp:12281:12"/>be vnderstood,<note place="margin">The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</note> first goeth about to plant in our harts the reuerence of the supreme magistrate, and teacheth vs that we ought not to admitte the contrarie for thought. Let vs therefore (leauing <hi>Rabbi Salomons</hi> allegorie of vnderstanding by King, God, which eateth out the heart of this text) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this doctrine of honouring the Prince in our heart, out of the heart of this scripture; and that also with the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of this scripture, to wit, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding a thousand suggestions of Satan to the contrarie. For such is the charge giuen of God on this behalfe in the fifth commandement, though the instance bee giuen of naturall parents: for it bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth proportion most pregnantly this way of all others. Honour (saith the Lord) thy Father and thy Mother, putting the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement in forme of an exhortation (as here) to make it more gracious there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as also by the promise annexed, as saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith. Neither hath the text barely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them,<note place="margin">Eph. 6</note> but by reason of the coniuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:12281:13"/>it weigheth as much as to prosecute them and loade them with honours, and with admiration of loue. The reasons to moue vs are very effectuall. For first wee cannot entertaine a sleight estimation of them without despising and despiting of God, who hath set his image, euen a coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall character vpon them, yea euen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those of them that knowe him not. Therefore the law saith,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note>
               <hi>Thou shalt not raile vppon the Gods,</hi> calling rulers Gods, which name also the holy ghost confesseth that he had bestowed vpon them,<note place="margin">Psalm. 82.6.</note>
               <hi>I sayde ye are Gods.</hi> And he hath not giuen them the name onely, but hee hath bestowed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so diuine gifts vpon them agreeable to the title. They are endewed (were not the word of God credible) with an incredible measure of wisedome, to speake euen ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles at times. When <hi>Saul</hi> at his inaugurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (saith the scripture) turned from <hi>Samuel, God gaue him another heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 10 9.</note> For the harts of princes are heroically endued with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, wisdome, and bountifulnes. And
<pb facs="tcp:12281:13"/>when neede requireth <hi>there shalbe</hi> (saith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>a diuine sentence in the lippes of a king,</hi> or other ruler for his places sake,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.10.</note> as wee read the diuine sentence of <hi>Salomon</hi> and of <hi>Caiphas.</hi> Whereby it is manifest,<note place="margin">1 King. 3. Ioh. 11.50.51.</note> that he that deiecteth the prince out of his conscience, deiecteth God himselfe, who requireth to sitte in his conscience by him. And God giueth vs no dispensation for any cause to disreuerence the prince, except that we be able to shew that we doe it as Gods commandement. The scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are plentifull in pleading for superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. And the men of god when they haue by mistaking, exceeded towardes a ruler (though a wicked one) haue vsed diligence to excuse themselues and to auoide the scandale.<note place="margin">Act. 23.5.</note>
               <hi>I knewe not</hi> (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that he was the high priest, for it is written, Thou shalt not curse the ruler of the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> And when they had proceeded beyond decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (though with speciall innocencie) yet they were troubled in conscience: for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was touched in his heart, because hee
<pb facs="tcp:12281:14"/>had cut off y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lap which was on <hi>Saules</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that if to refuse God be vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, then it must needes be so to admit a contemptuous thought of a prince, in whom God offereth himselfe vnto vs: I say a contemptuous thought, for both this text is so, &amp; also the law is spiritual. And it is so sure that they are vngodly men which offend in this kinde, that the holy ghost calleth them <hi>sonnes of Belial,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10 27.</note> that is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yoked persons, which refuse to bee vnder the yoke of due obedience.</p>
            <p>But what can bee obiected? truely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in effect, but that men haue taken a toye to scue like vnbroken horses from their duetie.</p>
            <p>As for the allegation made by here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes of conscience to God. When no dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to God is required, it is in great hypocrisie that God is alleadged: for are they not put togither in scripture,<note place="margin">Prou. 24 21. 1. Pet. 2 17 Rom. 13 2.7</note>
               <hi>Feare God and the King, and depart from the sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> (as it is translated) or (as the text hath it) <hi>from the various,</hi> from those that deuide
<pb facs="tcp:12281:14"/>these dueties, so as if they could not consist togither. And did not both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> require so much, when kings were enemies of the truth, and of the saluation of their subiects? Verily, when men make their scuse by God in this behalfe, they doe no better, <hi>then tell a lie for the Almightie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 13.9</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> saith in another matter. For <hi>that which is Caesars, may be giuen to Caesar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 22 21</note> without the least breach of allegiance to almightie God. And it is most true that <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saith vpon the 13. to the Romans,<note place="margin">Hom. 23</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; subiection to Princes ouerturneth not religion. A point belike that in those daies stood in need still &amp; successiuely to be vrged. For the Greeke Scholiast likewise in his collect vpon the same place to the Rom.<note place="margin">Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</note> hath it neere word for word. And he saith after, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> taketh great care to vrge it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euerie where. Neither was this (as <hi>Ierom</hi> suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth) by reason of the continuance of any olde heresie: but because S. <hi>Paul</hi> saw that this sin would vniuersally and successiuely
<pb facs="tcp:12281:15"/>assaile. For it hath euer beene a world of tongues; and as for thoughts, men thinke they are lawlesse. But assuredly whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer men perswade themselues, though the external subiection be neuer so strict; yet the contemptuous thought of a Prince (though the disreuerence be neuer so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret) cannot stand with true and vndefiled religion. For the conscience that is guiltie of quarrelsome thoughts against the lords annointed (how close soeuer they be kept) is wrecked. And such a man is forsaken of the holy ghost, and is solde to an vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable criminousnesse in other things besides that. As we reade in <hi>Iude,</hi> that <hi>they are filthy persons that despise gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. Iudae ver. 8</note> And (as <hi>Peter</hi> saith) <hi>bruit beasts, lead by sensualitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12</note>
               <hi>which haue no ground but ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance for their deed.</hi> And therefore as men tender the worke of godlines in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, they must keepe tenderly in the reines of their consciences the reuerence of their prince.</p>
            <p>But what say the Rhemists to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?
<pb facs="tcp:12281:15"/>Forsooth <hi>that euerie man must not be subiect to all that be in office, or superioritie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Annotat. in Ro. 13</note>
               <hi>but euerie one to him whom God hath put in authority ouer him, by that he is his superior, and that onely in matters of peace and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp;c. but not in matters of religion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of soules.</hi> Where note first that these counterfait Catholicks haue taken li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to change euen their ciuill superior (as you know the storie of Storie) and that howsoeuer they pretend to be subiect in matters of policie, yet they be not without their euasion. For euen matters of policie must be iudged to be matters of religion, and matters of regiment of soules, if their spiritual superiour doe once so deem them and doome them: yea (which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of all absurditie to holde, and the quintessence of treacherie to resolue of) they play fast and loose, and submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with a <hi>quatenus,</hi> a popish one I wis, no longer then till they be strong enough to resist and rebell, for then they holde their consciences discharged. And so may
<pb facs="tcp:12281:16"/>Princes see what sure cardes they haue of Papists.</p>
            <p>But let vs leaue them, and let vs come to our selues, who by the grace of God doe protest our obedience to our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, not after a popish, that is to say, a sophisticall manner. For although you be not to bee challenged of disloialtie, so that <hi>you should need to bee spoken to</hi> (to imitate Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> wordes) <hi>as touching the loue of your Prince,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Thes. 4.9.10.</note>
               <hi>for we are taught of God to loue such a Prince, yea and that thing verily you doe: yet we beseech you brethren that you increase more and more.</hi> It is not to be doubted but Satan, as he hath alreadie, so he will practise the contrarie with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and wil turne himselfe into euerie like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to preuaile. Whosoeuer doth vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend his Soueraigne in his conscience, is either an Atheist, or an Hypocrite. But because Satan will teach vs to be mad with reason, let vs I pray you without offence of any for our better preseruatiue, consider further what grieuous sins (in steed of what
<pb facs="tcp:12281:16"/>great reasons) Satan will vse to peruert our hearts, and to sollicite vs to entertaine a colder estimatiō of so honored a Queene, as God hath blessed vs withall.</p>
            <p>First he wil worke by our pride. For (as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith) though men alleadge other scuses,<note place="margin">The first cause of vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Prou. 13.10.</note> yet <hi>pride onely is the source of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi> For subiects haue seldome hearts humble enough, especially they that haue any wit are rarely found to haue the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of wisedome. And thus it commeth to passe, that their conceitednes redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the disreuerence of their Prince. And in verie truth, the land is full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited persons of this kinde, whose harts are sowred with the leauen of their owne pride: insomuch that oftentimes there ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth a bitternesse out of the stomacke of malecontents into their mouths, whē their wilfull ruines are not repaired by Princes; so that they cannot forbeare to speake of the sacred Maiestie of a Prince with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and ridiculous mouth. The Caual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieroes liberal science hath many vncouth
<pb facs="tcp:12281:17"/>positions, as that stabbing is necessarie for tempering of toongs, that it is a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all manhood to take the lie. And this is one of the rules of the same newe learning, which wilde creatures haue brought into the world, euen a doctrine of <hi>Belial,</hi> for a man to dare to speake what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer commeth in his head. And men are so foolish to thinke, that standers by will ascribe greatnesse vnto them, if they giue euidence of an impudent and audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous spirit by their words. And yet there want not pretences, as of ingenuousnesse, or of spirits, or of martiall education, or of zeale to their countrey. But let vs not be deceiued, for a man may be free born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a free tongue, and a man may abound in spirits, without despising the spirit of modestie: he may be a souldier though his face bee not made of harnesse: hee may be zealous and be no incendiarie. It were much to be wished, that our humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might keep our thoughts in better tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and therefore much more put our
<pb facs="tcp:12281:17"/>tongues to silence. For what are subiects in comparison of Princes? If the Iewes were commanded to <hi>put their neckes vnder the yoke of the king of Babel,</hi> and <hi>to pray for the peace of Nebuchadnezzar</hi> an heathen ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, how should not we buckle our selues to a greater humilitie of minde, to a prince that excelleth <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> as much as a Diamond excelleth a pibble stone? There was enacted since her Maiesties raigne a statute of words and rumours, and that vnder no greater penaltie then deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And it were to be wished, though not vnder so great penalty, yet vnder some due penaltie, such as might be warranted by Gods word, that the same statute might extend to all words whatsoeuer, that are wilfully and scornfully cast out to any kind of violating, or disreuerence of the honour of the Prince, though cloaked by meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For now adaies many that professe irregularitie, if they get betweene the pot and the wall, doe despise all rules of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, and their instrument goeth volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
<pb facs="tcp:12281:18"/>It were a great indignitie to denie that men of valour are verie honourable and necessarie instruments. But there are that go vnder the name of resolute, which giue occasion to vpbraide the land, as <hi>Ezechiel</hi> vpbraided Ierusalem. <hi>There are in thee that haue despised father and mother,</hi> that speake scornfully both of Queene and counsell.<note place="margin">Eze. 22.7.</note> If it went no further then thoughts, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment were restrained to the iudge of thoughts; but when it bursteth foorth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire of words, it behooueth men to powre water vpon it. The common wealth hath been greatly damnified in the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of virgines, in the education of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and otherwise with this new precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate position of cockering of spirits, and specially the estimation of Princes is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated thereby: so that he which will purge himselfe from this vice, had need to thinke more lowly of himselfe, and more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his prince. And so much of pride as it doth preiudice mans duetie to his prince.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:18"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cause of vndueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes.</note>The second way whereby Satan goeth about to abuse persons, otherwise not euill, and so to inueigle them to abuse their Prince, is lacke of wisedome in not discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the lawfulnesse of sundrie pretences, and policies of Princes, and their foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to condemne their princes therefore. It is true, that <hi>we may not doe euill that good may come therof:</hi> I say, we may not doe it: &amp; that we must <hi>auoide the verie appearance of an euill deede,</hi> to wit, such as might mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster any iust occasion to a wise and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man to suspect vs; yet we must not liue by the fooles lore. To disguise a purpose with a pretence, is not forbidden by the word of God. It behooueth vs to make a good constructiō of the intents of Princes, and it is an vncomely thing to take vpon vs the censuring of the meanes, whereby they are contriued. Wee are not worthie to know them. There is indeed no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison with God: but because it is his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to call Kings gods, therefore wee may partly impart this saying in <hi>Iob</hi>-vnto them,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:19"/>that as <hi>The Lord giueth not account of all his matters,</hi> so in some respect it may bee said of Princes. The holy Ghost hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs all, but most of all to them the <hi>Wisedome of serpents,</hi> so it bee qualified with the <hi>Innocencie of Doues.</hi> And it is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied both in God, and in the child of God, which the holy Ghost saith,<note place="margin">Prou. 8 12</note>
               <hi>I Sapience dwel with prudence.</hi> Pretences and deedes doe often require no other correspondence, then is betweene the face of a Ferie man and his oares. But there are some which haue so distasted the very name of policie, as if it were the name of some fowle vice. And many of these which crie for a plaine course, and to keepe in the rode way, are themselues (as <hi>Salomon</hi> before saith) so sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that they scarse knowe the way home: so that they giue occasion to inuert the verse. <hi>Quicquid delirat populus rex plecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> the peoples dotage turneth to the kinges blame. <hi>Salomon</hi> pretended to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide an infant to good purpose, and did not. <hi>Paul</hi> pretended to <hi>Iudaize,</hi> and did
<pb facs="tcp:12281:19"/>not; he shore his head in Cenchrea, hee tooke vpon him to bee a votarie, hee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised <hi>Timothy,</hi> he purified himselfe: yea to escape the Sadduces he pretēded to be a Pharisie, by the aduantage of holding one thing with the Pharisies. Doth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost (which praised <hi>Salomon</hi> for the like) detect him; or else doth it commend him for these thinges? Or would <hi>Paul</hi> haue blamed <hi>Peter</hi> and others, because they did not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, went not with a right foote, if hee had been guiltie of a wrie course in himselfe? It is verie obseruable, that the same Apostle which abounded in giftes and graces, abounded in godly poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. I speake not this as a patron of irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious policies, but onely to auoide the absolute condēnation of that which gods word somewaie alloweth. Be sure of it that this folly is a great fault, and when it is busie folly it is a great interrupter of princes in their holesome attempts, as it had fallen out if any had taken exception to <hi>Salomons</hi> commaundement of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12281:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12281:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:12281:21"/>the infant. It behooueth the body to receiue sense from the head; but it doth not become Idiots to coniure the doings of princes within the circle of their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>A third sinne which the Diuell inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth into the people,<note place="margin">The third cause of vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> and thereby sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth an vnreuerent conceit of their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnto them, is lacke of compassion in not weighing their temptations and their necessities. There is no doubt but sinne is sinne in whomsoeuer, in King or Kaesar: and there is as little doubt of this, that sinne is to be extenuated or aggrauated by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances. <hi>We ought</hi> (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> saith) <hi>to carrie one anothers burthen.</hi> It is a great iniurie which is offered to princes, and it is verie disagrecable with charitie, when an vniust rate is set either vpon their defects or their vertues. They themselues ought not to giue their consciences any vnlawfull libertie before God. But subiects that aile nothing, and are better supplied with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies against sin then princes be, ought
<pb facs="tcp:12281:21"/>of right to allow them a great deale of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-measure in this behalfe. For subiects haue a benefit of the discipline of lawes to curbe them for stumbling, and the raines thereof to holde them from falling. But when kings are considered comparatiuely with inferiour persons, they are found to trauell with the winde and stormes in their faces, when others haue it on their backes. Now this disaduantage must finde at our hands good allowance another way. For when wheries meet on the Thames, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage and shelter of the banke is theirs of right, that haue the winde and tide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. Princes haue riches and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which are (as <hi>Isocrates</hi> saith) facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of misdoing. They haue nothing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to implead allurements, but the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare of God: and on the other side ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours come to them at the first hand, to enforce discouragements: so that it is a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall mercie of God to many of them, and to their subiects in them, that they doe so well as they doe. Once it is an vndoubted
<pb facs="tcp:12281:22"/>truth, that not one of their deprauers would approach to them in vertues, if (<hi>cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris paribus,</hi> that is to say, if circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were matches) they were in their places.</p>
            <p>But it may be obiected, that a mans sin is amplified and not diminished by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance of being a Magistrate, as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Aug. in li. quaest. vet. et nom testamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. 16</note>
               <hi>Viri sublimis culpa graue pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum est,</hi> the fault of a man of place, is a grieuous sinne. This is so to be deemed in deed in respect of extorting his lusts by his magistracie, or for defiling Gods seate of iustice; or in respect of the effect, when the Magistrate maketh no conscience of his doings that are exemplarie, being <hi>duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor populi,</hi> the leader of the people, as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> saith in the same place. Otherwise the circumstance of power and prosperitie considered as meerely personall, extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth a mans sinne when his case is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with theirs, whose temptations Satan cannot manage by these meanes: so that the matter lieth vnder such a distinction,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:22"/>as diuideth the sentence betweene aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating and extenuating.</p>
            <p>And that in this case it is the duetie of the Magistrate himselfe, to aggrauate his owne offence by the circumstance of his place: and the duetie of others, to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the personall offences of princes by the circumstaunce of their temptations. In deed foule circumstances make foul faults, as when <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke <hi>Vrijahs</hi> wife, and had all <hi>Saules</hi> wiues before, and when the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites tempted God so often in the WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERNES, euen in the schoole of the crosse. But there are other circumstaunces that should mollifie vs, and teach vs to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the errors of others in our consciences, as when a <hi>man stealeth to satisfie his soule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou 6 30.</note>
               <hi>because he is hungrie.</hi> Also we must not be too vrgent vpon princes, but ought to allow a longer time of nauigation in winter then in sommer. Some haue an opinion, that the pleasures and magnificence of princes take away their vnderstanding. But <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>I was great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 2 9</note>
               <hi>and yet my wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:12281:23"/>remained with mee.</hi> Others thinke that princes are inexcusable, if they abate of their magnanimitie for any cause. But <hi>Dauid</hi> saith,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.39.</note>
               <hi>I am weake and newly annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and they are too hard for mee.</hi> And to <hi>Abishai</hi> counselling him to put <hi>Shimei</hi> to death (though he had right well deserued it) he replieth,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 19 20.22.</note>
               <hi>that he counselled him then like an enemy to mooue him to put any body to death, seeing he knew, that he was but that day as it were newly restored king ouer Israel.</hi> Had it not been for healing circumstances,<note place="margin">2 King. 18 15</note> it had been a crime in <hi>Hezekiah</hi> &amp; a plaine sacrilege, to inrich <hi>Senacherib</hi> with the spoile of the temple. It had deserued no lesse the reprehension of the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers. 9.10</note> then his ostentation to the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But for as much as <hi>Samaria was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie taken, and all the strong Cities of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> his weaknesse was a great deale more excusable in the eies of all those which haue learned any compassion of others, by the conscionable feeling of their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:23"/>
            <p> Thinke the same thing of the vertues of princes, that they are to be valued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly aboue their appearance, and aboue the selfesame deedes in othermen. The reason is the circumstance of their royall person, which ministreth an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this question, both from the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cause and from the effect. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the argument from the efficient cause, obserue that the good deed of a king is kingly, whereby he sheweth that hee doth not onely sustaine the person of a king by his office, but is also a king perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by his mind and heart. Athough al vertues be morall, that is to say, taught in the morall law; yet the vertues of men as they are Christians are onely vsually so called. And as for the vertues of gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and administration of a common wealth, they are called politique vertues. Now although the morall vertues be most necessary, that the person of the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate maie be accepted in respect of a sanctified conscience before God; yet
<pb facs="tcp:12281:24"/>know you that as moral vertues are essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to Christians, so politique vertues are essentiall to princes: and that the politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vertues of true Christian princes are more excellent for the profit of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, then their morall vertues bee. Thinke with thy selfe then, that to do the office of a King, is a supereminent vertue; and a thing so necessarie to bee don, that by a rule of Gods word other personall dueties not onely may, but must giue place and bee pretermitted at that time for the performance thereof. It is true indeed, that if princes will causeleslie pretend their office to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues from the personall dueties of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and charitie, which belong to their vocation of christianitie, that they do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please almightie God. But otherwise the necessitie of a generall duetie to God, and so iustly conceiued of by the doer, dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth with the omission of any inferior duetie.</p>
            <p>It is found, and worthily to due purpose
<pb facs="tcp:12281:24"/>alleaged <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46. <hi>that the prince shall go into the temple when the people go in,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 46 10.</note>
               <hi>and when they go out they shall go out togither.</hi> It is sure enough that a fit man that had accesse, might giue princes godly aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisements out of that scripture, yet the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may not take occasion thereby to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge princes whatsoeuer necessity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straineth them, for not doing so euery Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. For that place, as appeareth in the verse next before it, speaketh of solemne feastes. And further it is (as all the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) an allegorie; and allegories make no rules in diuinitie. It were to bee wished in deed, that the law in the 17. of <hi>Deut.</hi> of the princes daily reading of the Scriptures, were obserued: but yet the people must suffer themselues to be informed, that this time, and that, seeme not all alike. For it doth not appeare vnto vs, that the Ciuill magistrates then had any other law-booke to study and peruse for ciuill administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but onely the Scriptures. Now then it must be ascribed in a king, that furnisheth
<pb facs="tcp:12281:25"/>his royal place duely, to a great measure of grace, if after his great labors in publique gouernment he do exercise himselfe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly in the publike seruice of God: Not because a moderate seruice of God doth suffice, but because the king hauing serued God before in his publicke calling (a duetie more incumbent) doth, if hee do well, serue him still when he is retired to priuate. And if with a wise heart wee would weigh thus much (and without iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging) wee would not suppose carefull princes to be so barren and vnfruitfull of good workes, as wee surmise (for a crowne is not good for the headach.) Nay wee would informe our heades with better thoughtes, and conforme our heartes to the sweetest affectiōs by viewing in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Queene (by no storie to be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry waie sampled) such wisedome in retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the trueth, such fortitude in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, such iustice in administrations, and such temperance in swaying of oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and those of so different natures. This
<pb facs="tcp:12281:25"/>is the argument from the efficient cause.</p>
            <p>The argument from the effect is, the great good that the vertue of a prince, though it be but of a small shew, doth. In which respect it may be said that princes haue no little vertues at all. For the very gratious behauior of a prince (saith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>is like the dew vpon the grasse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19 12.</note> and his very presence doth both honor and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage any good action.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fourth cause of vndueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes.</note>The fourth sin, whereby Satan maimeth the good conceit of the soueraigne in the heart of a subiect, is lacke of equity in the subiect, when he blameth this prince for his owne fault. For wee require confident proceeding of princes: and yet wee do weaken them with our owne distraction. It is sin in vs to be distracted, and it is yet a greater sin to thinke hardlie of others, for the fault which wee haue committed.<note place="margin">Prou. 30.29.3</note>
               <hi>It is in deed</hi> (as in the Prou. it is said) <hi>a comely thing for a king, against whom there is no ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vp, to go on forward.</hi> But the wretched dissension of subiects is a kind of rising vp,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:26"/>&amp; doth too often alter the case. The distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the people is like the pestilence in-an armie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hindereth it from marching for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Neither is it possible for the prince to be so cōfident in rooting out of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites, after Israel is departed from Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, as before. The children of Israel (saith the holy Ghost) were staied longer then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary at Hazeroth,<note place="margin">Numb. 11 45. and Num. 12.</note> till <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were censured by God for murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Moses,</hi> and after were reconciled. The whole host was arrested by this distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not by <hi>Moses</hi> his lingering.</p>
            <p>Let vs iudge righteous iudgement, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the diuision of the land, and the subdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision also, haue not hindered the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the prince. The diuision is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Catholiques (as they will needs be called) and Protestants: &amp; one subdiuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is betweene protestants and Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (and that a shrewde one) which is raised to as high a price as alienation of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the sting of the tongue, and the
<pb facs="tcp:12281:26"/>tooth of the pen could enhance it. And besides that distraction, which properly respecteth the controuersie it selfe, it hath brought forth these two effects, that wee will neither vouchsafe to seeme to consent, in that wherein wee do consent, <hi>to walke by one rule in that whereunto we are come;</hi> nor ioine togither against the common aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie. In the meane while the Tabernacle is set downe at Hazeroth, &amp; (as our enemies do hope) is more like to goe backe to Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broth-hattauah, then to go forward to the-wildernes of Paran. Many hard and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guised courses haue been taken, tēding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an inexpiable diuision, as that by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> with the wild oppositions of that kind. (Hee hath not a godly eare that can not endure the rebuke of that sinne, I saie hee hath not a godly eare.) If you will giue me leaue to detect by the stratagē of the deuil the stage-plaiers leasing of deuils, they plaied the part of fained deuils so long, till at last there was found a deuill more then tale, which hath driuen them from the
<pb facs="tcp:12281:27"/>stage; I meane the Papist with his preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to the discomfort of all Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. They in deed were <hi>diaboli personati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait diuels. A diuell in good er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest.</note> but he is <hi>diabolus personalis et verus.</hi> Since that distraction wee haue stoode mutually excommunicated one in anothers consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Then was the wofull childbirth of <hi>Elies</hi> daughter in law at the taking of the Arke. Then was <hi>Ichabod</hi> born, for then the glorie departed from Israel,<note place="margin">Ichabod 1 Sam. 4 21</note> for since that eclipse the gospel hath shined dimmer &amp; dimmer. We are to be beseeched to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke vs of the calamities of the times; let vs not make a vertue of necessitie, but ioine a vertue to necessitie, &amp; conuert al the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions offered to opportunitie of fighting for the common faith. Let vs lay aside the preiudice of our owne deed, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of other mens deedes; and bethinke vs in the highnesse of humilitie, and not in the highnesse of conceit, what is fit to be don in this case: otherwise let vs not blame the prince but our selues.</p>
            <p>There remaineth now the last cause of
<pb facs="tcp:12281:27"/>the decaie of reuerent affection to princes, the forgetfulnes of their benefits, which in one worde is vnthankfulnes. <hi>Weepe</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid</hi> to the daughters of Israel) <hi>for Saule which clothed you in skarlet with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.24.</note>
               <hi>and hanged ornaments of gold vpon your apparell.</hi> And <hi>Ieremie</hi> saith of <hi>Iosiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lamen. 4.24</note>
               <hi>that he was the breath of their nostrils, and that vnder his shadow, they had been preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aliue among the heathen.</hi> But men are very vngratious in forgetting their princes, &amp; the blessings of God receiued by them, and fall awaie in their hearts by little and little. Let vs take heed that wee of this nation, wrap not our selues in this sinne. As for the Papists which haue made rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and conspiracie, as it were an article of their creed, their sinne in this behalfe is written with the claw of a adamant, in a table of remembraunce before both God and man for all posteritie. Let vs bethinke vs conscionably how much we are bound to our gratious Queene, and not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull, but thankfull.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:28"/>
            <p> First she hath beene our <hi>Iosiah,</hi> for shee hath restored the law that was lost. Secōd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, she hath beene our <hi>Iehoshaphat,</hi> in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Iudges to execute, not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of man, but of the Lord. Thirdly, she hath beene our <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> she hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the doores of the Temple of the Lord the first yeare and the first moneth. Fourthly, she hath beene our <hi>Dauid,</hi> for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter great affliction most innocently &amp; with memorable grace endured, she came into the throne of Maiestie, to settle peace and comfort in the throne of our conscience; yea to erect a throne for Christ to sit in, in the conscience of euerie man that would receiue him, by <hi>giuing vs lawes in which we may liue.</hi> Fiftly, she hath beene our <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> for she hath brought and continued aboundance of peace. By the benefit which God hath bestowed vpon her to bestowe vpon vs (which also she hath bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs) The saying of the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> is verified amongst vs.<note place="margin">Iere. 48.11.</note>
               <hi>We haue been at rest from our youth, and haue setled on our lees,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:28"/>and haue not been powred from vessell to ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell.</hi> We haue endured no change, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our taste remaineth in vs, and our sent is not changed.</hi> If our thrift had been aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the meanes, the wealth of the land had been incredible. Shee hath been carefull for vs like a mother, which waketh that her children may sleepe. The worke of our protection hath prospered maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously in her hand, and Gods protection ouer her infoldeth as many of vs, as be not drawne to reuerence her thereby, in a grieuous crime. Her right is good, her gouernment good, her successe good, let our hearts also be good. Her continuance encreaseth her reuerence and authoritie, if we decrease not in the grace of God. The holy Scripture saith,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21 17.</note> that <hi>Dauid</hi> was the <hi>light of Israel</hi> when he had raigned long. Her sex is legitimated with this honour by the fift commandement, no lesse then the naturall mother ouer her naturall children. <hi>Honor</hi> thy father and <hi>thy mother.</hi> And may we not truely say (and that without iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing)
<pb facs="tcp:12281:29"/>that <hi>the Rauens of the valley haue pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out the eies of many of her despisers?</hi> And what thinke we? not only of our duetie, but also of the measure of our duetie? Doth not this text priuiledge her, and preferre her aboue all other subordinate powers in assigning her the reuerence of the heart, and to them the reuerence of the tongue? It ought to be so farre from vs to seat any in our hearts before her, or in any degree e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with her, that when any person either opposeth himselfe vnto her, or seeketh to equall his interest in the hearts of her sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects with hers, we are bound in conscience to extirpe and exterminate him out of our hearts. It is but the wisedome of the flesh to leane to hopes, and to swarue from feare of future things, with any abatement of the present duetie. And it is not to haue a care of the Church, to be mindelesse of a present blessing, whilest we are looking this way and that way into the corners of the world. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is our Sparta, let vs adorne her; let vs desire of God with
<pb facs="tcp:12281:29"/>earnest prayers the defeating of all wicked hopes, and the long and verie long defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all hopes whatsoeuer.</p>
            <p>There is not one man in all these domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that desireth a change, except he be giuen ouer into a reprobate sense; and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purposeth to be an agent of great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, or foreseeth not to be a patient of great miseries. There are two cruell beasts in the land with gaunt bellies, the <hi>wickedly needy,</hi> and the <hi>wickedly moody.</hi> The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly needy are they in all degrees which haue consumed their own estates, and now houer ouer other mens, and therefore their eie watcheth for the twilight. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly moody are they, which haue treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp wrath and reuenge in their mindes against those, which haue been Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments for their nurture. These haue disdained that due defence should be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to their vnduetifull offence. Both these (as it is said of Lyons) haue for the time crookt in their nailes to keepe them sharpe: but they looke for a day, and God
<pb facs="tcp:12281:30"/>grant to as many among them as be impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, a day, &amp; that the day that they shall see may be (as <hi>Zacharie</hi> saith) <hi>when their eies shall sincke in their holes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 14 12.</note>
               <hi>and their toong shall consume in their mouth;</hi> and in the meane time, <hi>that their flesh may consume away, though they stand vpon their feete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It must not be thought that this is to preach men, but that this is to preach to men, to teach them to glorifie God in his ordinance, and to keep peace in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. And I would to God with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of all opinion of discretion, that this were not more then needfull to be vrged to many, that haue iudued themselues with no small reputation of their owne suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie. Interpret me charitably, I am se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for my selfe, but I take care for you that you sin not in vncharitable surmises.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the next point, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are counselled not to curse the rich, not to depraue persons of dignitie, which by the appointment of princes doe excell in authoritie: <hi>Curse not</hi> (saith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>the
<pb facs="tcp:12281:30"/>rich, no not in the withdrawing of thy bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.</hi> The word of God hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs the supreme Magistrate, or Prince alone: but the subordinate and subalternall Magistrate also,<note place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the subal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall magistrate</note> such as he shal adhibit to the administration of thinges, they are both in the principall commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And marke well this point, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the subordinate Magistrate hath his commission out of a commission in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Prince, and that, <hi>durante bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placito;</hi> yet he hath it so long, as the Prince is so pleased, immediately from God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of our conscience. Obserue the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Apostles both <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter: Put them in remembrance</hi> (saith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that they be subiect to principalities and</hi> To POVVERS,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1</note>
               <hi>and that they be ohedient and ready to euerie good worke, that they speake euill of none.</hi> And againe, <hi>pray for kings and all that are in authoritie,</hi> to wit, vnder them. And S. <hi>Peter</hi> saith:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note>
               <hi>Submit your selues to all manner ordinance of man for the Lords sake, whether it be vnto the king as vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:12281:31"/>superiour, or vnto gouernours as vnto them that are sent of him.</hi> And to returne to S. <hi>Paul,</hi> he saith of all in generall thus consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>that the powers that be are ordained of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> both supreme and subordinate, they are ordained by speciall institution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will reuealed, and are not meer effects of his prouidence, as heretikes haue thought. S. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed to note constraint, saith, <hi>that resisters shall receiue to themselues iudgement:</hi> but in the meane while he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>that we must be subiect also for consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence sake. For this cause</hi> (saith <hi>Augustine</hi>) <hi>ne quis non pura dilectione subditus fieret huiusmodi potestatibus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">August in expos. prop. in ep. ad Ro. propos. 74.</note> least any in their subiection to such powers should be defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in sincere loue. <hi>We must doe it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for conscience sake, that is, that we may be sure in our conscience that we doe it with the loue of them, to whom we are subiect, ius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su domini nostri, at our Lords hest:</hi> (after his words) and as you may adde further, <hi>iussu dominae nostrae, at the commandement of our Ladies Lord.</hi> We must therefore not rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon
<pb facs="tcp:12281:31"/>it for seruited to bee vnder so many, but bee subiect with an ingenuous spirit. They that are otherwise affected, are like the base minded hindes, and apprentices to the plow, which say they like well their maister and their mistris, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the bailiffe of the husbandry, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> setteth them to worke. An homly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison will serue such homly folke. The speeches both of the vulgar and others to, which magnifie their mouthes aboue the assise, are many both against the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and actions of magistrates, and they are fraught with speciall indecencie to a ciuill eare, and with scandalous wickednes to a man of gratious vnderstanding. But let vs examine as in the prohibition, so in this inhibition the reason of these doings.</p>
            <p>First if wee will inquire, we shall find one ground of this deed to bee enuie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such persons of worth are (lightly) rich, as they haue their denomination in this text. There is a great complaint of their couetousnes, &amp; their endles getting.
<pb facs="tcp:12281:32"/>A thing indeed very worthy to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into by themselues, how far their guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines doth stretch in this behalfe: But it is not worthy to be inquired into by vs; but least of all in an vnworthy manner. What thinke wee? that <hi>they which must giue a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to seuen and also to eight</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith) <hi>hath not neede to cast their bread vpon the waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 11 1.2</note> that is to saie, to make prouisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the meanes,<note place="margin">Vide Tre. mehum.</note> as it is best expoūded? Dowe thinke that when men are aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be ministers of the state, they may not both entertaine and procure also good meanes, to inrich themselues for the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of their degree? I cannot tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the malignity or ignorance of men be greater, or whether the hypocrisie of some be not greatest of all, which can finde in their hearts to inrich themselues, &amp; to on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy others for so doing. Had not <hi>Ioseph</hi> so inriched himselfe that hee nourished his father and all his family? <hi>It is not indecent</hi> (saith <hi>Augustine</hi>) <hi>to desire sufficientiam vitae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. de orando deo ad Probam.</note> And he defineth sufficiency of life to
<pb facs="tcp:12281:32"/>be (among other thinges) <hi>propter congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem habitum personae hominis, that his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour</hi> (as he further saith) <hi>may not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient to those with whom he must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse.</hi> And hee concludeth, <hi>Ista ergo cum habentur vt teneantur, cum autem non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur vt habeantur orandum est. These things while wee haue them wee must pray to hold them, and when wee haue them not, to haue them.</hi> I may truly speake it, and with greater libertie to, of those that are departed, that this land hath enioyed great counsellours and other ministers of state, which haue gotten much (in deede) and yet no more the might very well bee vouchsafed them, if there were an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing heart in men to value such perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages according to their worth. It is not a sufficient cause to maligne their riches &amp; aduauncements, which giue their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the safetie of prince and state. But their care and prouidence is a merit of a greater matter, and the maligning of thē is a demerit of a greater rebuke then fitteth
<pb facs="tcp:12281:33"/>me to giue. What is the obiection of new Nobilitie worth, when it shall be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighed with their new desert of quitting themselues so worthily in the managing of this noble state, as sundrie haue done suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessiuely, from the beginning of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties raigne till now?</p>
            <p>Secondly, vpon enquirie it will be euin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that the cause of deprauing magistrats is the incorrigiblenes of the euill disposed. They crie out of crueltie against some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Iudges and Magistrates, when their amendment is sought by anie due seuerity. And although wee be fallen into an age, whose diseases are growne to a Gangrene, yet we fare as they which had rather leese their life then a member. It were a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing to men in the behalfe of their owne innocencie, to be carefull how they presumed to taxe the innocencie of those Magistrates that are zealous iusticers, and to commend those for harmelesse which are languishing and loose in this dutie. When sin is growne to an head (as among
<pb facs="tcp:12281:33"/>vs) it is time for the Magistrate to make head against it. He must punish extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie wickednesse with extraordinarie se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie, as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>The blewnesse of the wound serueth to purge the euill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20.30.</note>
               <hi>and the stripes within the bowels of the belly.</hi> For (as <hi>Augustine</hi> saith) <hi>Sicuti est aliquando miseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia puniens, ita &amp; crudelitas parcens:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium. epist. 64.</note> There is a punishing mercie, and a sparing crueltie. And if the Ammonites which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated King <hi>Dauids</hi> seruants so villanously might haue caried it away so, what end would haue beene put to such insolencies by the Gentiles? And therefore the holy Ghost saith in commendation of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that <hi>he put them vnder sawes, and harrowes, and axes of yron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12 31.</note>
               <hi>and cast them into the tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kilnes.</hi> The tongues of Acolasts are no slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For whatsoeuer they say, if God had not directed her Maiestie in placing such Magistrates as she hath don, it would haue redounded to the dishonour of God, to her dangerous disseruice, and to the spoile of her people.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:34"/>
            <p> Thirdly, men of a slaunderous and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging spirit, set their fanges vpon the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of state as vpon irreligious persons, bearing themselues &amp; others in hand, that they are of no religion, and that they make no conscience of any thing. Of this kind the greatest part are either fooles or facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; being heated with a faction can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce themselues to beleeue without argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For what? is discerning betweene humor and spirit Atheisme? It standeth personages of state in hand to looke well to their owne hearts, for these men will not looke to their tongues. For although they occupie not their tongues in praying for them, yet they occupie them in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: and what lacketh that of Atheisme? For as one saith, there is Atheisme in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres as well as in Lucretius. As many as haue good consciences <hi>neede not to passe of it</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saieth) <hi>to bee iudged of the daie of man.</hi> And the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues which whisper such thinges, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the Lord doth not measure
<pb facs="tcp:12281:34"/>an Atheist by their report. For (as <hi>Ierom</hi> saith) <hi>non eadē est sententia tribunalis Dei et anguli susurronum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Epist. ad virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note> The sentence of Gods Tribunal and the whisperers angle, is not al one. We ought not to iudge: but whē satan is once moūted vpō his black steed (I mean y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> suspicious melancholie of a man) he will condemne <hi>Hushai</hi> himself as an Atheist,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.18.</note> for his semblance of reuolting to <hi>Absalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bee breise, men haue so many vices in themselues, wherewith to depraue the vertues of magistrates, that they can almost do nothing by them with a good report. Sometimes their sufficiencie is depraued; sometimes their fidelitie challenged; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their actions carped at; and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their states are enuied. They that are so lauish in this behalfe, might bee po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with three questions when they enter into these secrets. First, how knowest thou? Secondly, what hast thou to doe with it? Thirdly, what true hatred of thine owne sin is in thee? How euer it be, it is the counsell of the holy ghost, more profitable
<pb facs="tcp:12281:35"/>for the malingners then their magistrates. <hi>Curse not the Rich, no not in thy bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The times wee are fallen into are both immodest, and vncharitable. It is of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modesty that many priuate men do (as it were) vsurpe vpon the intelligence of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry secrets of the politique conueiance, &amp; gouernment. It is lawfull for vs to informe our selues (if wee can by good meanes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto it) of state matters, that are not impertinent vnto vs to direct our prayers. But it is neither lawful to be eauesdroppers of state to occupie our toongs, nor to make an occupation of intelligencing when we are priuate men. It is his protestation that had the holie Ghost,<note place="margin">Psalm. 131.</note>
               <hi>I haue not walked in great matters and hid from mee.</hi> And it is his sonnes speech that hath the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of wisedome from the holy ghost, that <hi>euery foole will bee medling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20.3.</note> Saint <hi>Peters</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1. Pe. 4.15. which is rendred <hi>busie body,</hi> reacheth in signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to one that is but <hi>inspector,</hi> a
<pb facs="tcp:12281:35"/>prier into other mens matters. And wee see in ecclesiasticall historians, that they which became <hi>Libellatici,</hi> that is, which were constrained to blaspheme Christ in writing, and they which were <hi>Thurificati,</hi> that is, which were constrained to offer sacrifices to the Diuell, (whereof <hi>Origen</hi> thorough his rashnesse was one) had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly beene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And it is of such, (as by conference of stories may bee collected) of whom <hi>Plinius Secundus</hi> writeth to his maister <hi>Traian: Coëgi eos maledicere Christo, I constrained them to curse Christ.</hi> A fearefull fruit of a busie bodie.</p>
            <p>To containe our selues within the boundes of our calling is a speciall point of christianitie. And there are many found that by their intrusion into other mens secrets, are brought to the foolish Poets complaint. <hi>Cur aliquid vidi?</hi> For it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the affectation of intelligence of doubtfull matters of state, to hurt the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers by their owne default. The reason is,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:36"/>because the tongue of such a man will take vengeance by talking shrewdly of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when the heart is grieued with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayes, and he will let driue at some in their absence, to whom hee would bow, if they were present. <hi>But if any man</hi> (saith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>long after life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.10.11.</note>
               <hi>and to see good daies, let him refraine his tongue from euill, and his lippes that they speake no guile. Let him eschewe euill, and do good; let him seeke peace and follow after it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is of vncharitablenesse that men are so credulous, when they heare hard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of great persons, and obserue not the rule of reports towards all persons. <hi>He cannot</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>be admitted into the fauour of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 15.3.</note>
               <hi>that is a taker vp of false reports that other men spread.</hi> There are many sent out by Satan to belie those that are in authoritie; but the Lord hath sent vs word by <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17.4.</note> that the <hi>wicked gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth heede to false lippes.</hi> The credulous in this kinde must needes be in danger, for the credulous in generall fare often
<pb facs="tcp:12281:36"/>worse then their informers. By reason of this sinne by Gods hand it came to passe, that the yoong Prophet which was credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, was preuented by death,<note place="margin">1. King. 13.17.18.</note> though the olde prophet, which was the seducer were respited aliue.</p>
            <p>Let vs not be transported with any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>indice at the hearing of these things, to hinder our edification. Neither let vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the worke of our sanctification, by these offences. If we apply our selues in sinceritie to ponder what is saide, the Lorde will giue vs vnderstanding in all thinges. And this for the first part.</p>
            <p>The second part consisting in the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment followeth. <hi>For the foule of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen shall carrie the voice, and that which hath winges shall declare the matter.</hi> In this place the Lord threatneth the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the deprauers of kings and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates. Now it is verie worthy to bee noted, that this threat proceedeth from the Holy Ghost himselfe, which is not without a remarqueable implication of
<pb facs="tcp:12281:37"/>the hainousnesse of this sinne. For the holy Ghost is not woont to bewray men for trifles: he onely interposeth himselfe to reueale, where sinners do specially op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselues to his grace, and to his Church or people. In which respect he emploied <hi>Elisha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 6.12.</note> to disclose to the king of Israel whatsoeuer the king of Aram spake in the withdrawing of his chamber. And he stirred vp <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19, 2.3.</note> to disclose to <hi>Dauid</hi> the secret conspiracies of <hi>Saul</hi> his owne father.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.11.12.</note> The like is testified of <hi>Michal,</hi> who (whatsoeuer she were otherwise) was led by the spirit of God in detecting the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bush of her father <hi>Saul.</hi> This proceeding of the holy ghost in taking the matter into his owne hand, to become both Oyer and Terminer, is strong euidence, that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligning of higher powers is in the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of those sinnes, which though they escape man, yet the vengeance of God doth pursue, and as it were bring backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the iudgement seate. So that it is not a good meaning, nor that we were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperate,
<pb facs="tcp:12281:37"/>which will serue for an excuse to pacifie our conscience. <hi>Parents offend if they prouoke their children to wrath;</hi> but is that any vvarrant for them to conceiue wrath? No: we must come with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of God for the least deed that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the defacing of the image of God. For els, whereas all true comfort is in the holy ghost, in this case the holy ghost is flat against vs.</p>
            <p>And as they are sinners with a witnesse, with whom the holy ghost himselfe is at the cost to be their detector, so marke like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, that by the same reason a man can haue no securitie in the secret committing of this. For this is an euill secret where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two cannot keepe counsell, though one be away. It is like the Iudaical leprosie, which resisted hypocriticall concealments by <hi>shewing it selfe in the forehead.</hi> For such kinde of persons are the Lordes Stigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, they are marked as <hi>Cain</hi> was.<note place="margin">1 Tmot. 5.25.</note> For (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> saith) <hi>things that are otherwise</hi> then well meant to Gods Church, <hi>cannot
<pb facs="tcp:12281:38"/>be hid.</hi> But let vs consider both the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers apart, for it is but a rule of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines to suppose it so verie frequent in scripture, to varie the words without any varietie of sense.</p>
            <p>Speaking of the latter member first, he saith, that if there be any maligning of the <hi>Rich</hi> (as he meaneth) <hi>the foules of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen shall carrie the voice:</hi> God will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the deprauation of the ministers of state appointed by the king, to escape vnreuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; nor consequently vnpunished.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Dauids</hi> deprauers, when he was but a subiect came after to shame and rebuke. And the prosperitie of <hi>Eliakim</hi> together with his aduauncement, is threatned to <hi>Shebna</hi> for maligning him being a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, and is ioyned to the threat of his aduersitie and ruine, as parcel of it.<note place="margin">Isaiah. 22.27.</note> So that although there be no expresse mention that <hi>Shebna</hi> was an enuier of <hi>Eliakim,</hi> yet the direction of the prophecie of <hi>Eliakims</hi> rising to <hi>Shebna</hi> (whom els it had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) discouereth both his sinne and his
<pb facs="tcp:12281:38"/>punishment. There are that thinke that if they can say, <hi>God saue the Queene,</hi> that it is as good as a preamble to scuse their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauing of the counsell. But if counsellors and other great magistrates doe beare the image of God, they beare also the name of God. And ye see what is repeated in the sanction of the third commaundement. The commandement is, <hi>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine:</hi> and the sanction is, <hi>for the Lord will not holde him guiltlesse that taketh his name in vaine.</hi> Marke how he repeateth, <hi>his name,</hi> to wit, in whomsoeuer represented, to terrifie vs not onely from maligning of Princes, but also from maligning of Magistrates, for the memorials of God are manifold. And though it might be that thy conscience did cleere thee of any wicked intention to the person of thy Prince, yet in that were thou not iustified before God, if thou meantst to supplant the authoritie of thy Princes counsell, and ministers of state: for that were indirectly to supplant the authoritie
<pb facs="tcp:12281:39"/>of thy Prince. It mattereth not what plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible shewes there be to doe such things, for the euent discouereth that they are but shewes. <hi>Absadom</hi> seemed to haue a iust quarrell against <hi>Amnon</hi> for lying with his sister, especially his pernicious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie considered by reason of <hi>Dauids</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. But <hi>Absaloms</hi> matter was not <hi>Amnons</hi> incest, but <hi>Ammons</hi> senio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; he was betwixt him and the crowne; for the euent declared what an hater of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest <hi>Absadom</hi> was, by his behauiour to his fathers concubines. And the Lorde discouered by his insurrection against his father, that it was ambition that made him to kill his brother. If we be endued with any christian docilitie, let vs receiue that which is sound with a simple heart. And let vs nurture our hearts with this truth, that God setteth himselfe to the reuenge of the iniuries done to subordinate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, which beare his image vpon earth; as he holdeth it blasphemie, not onely <hi>to blaspheme himselfe and his taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 13.6.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12281:39"/>
               <hi>but also those that dwell in heauen:</hi> I offer vnto you that which is first offered to me by the word of God, togither with the due consideration and affection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite in such a speech, and so I leaue both you and it to the Lord. Onely be of a wise heart, and beware of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of sinne. Your children (you say) will go from a pinne to a point, and so further: feare the like proceedings in this grieuous matter. For they that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauers of deputed Magistrates, their tongues will afterward light vpon the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme. This of the latter member set for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in the Argument.</p>
            <p>Now speaking of the former member in the latter place, hee saith, that if there be any maligning of the King; <hi>the maister of the wings shall declare the matter.</hi> His mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that the Lord by his administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will bee a swift witnes, and by his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution a swift iudge against such. For they presume very neere him that reach to his annointed, and to his children: For Kings
<pb facs="tcp:12281:40"/>and Queenes by an excellencie are called the sons and daughters of God, and hee watcheth ouer them with a celestiall care. There is a memorable storie in the second or <hi>Esther</hi> of the discouerie of a treason, wherein also there are many momorable obseruations closely couched togither.<note place="margin">Esther. 2.21.22.</note> The storie is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Mordecai</hi> detected the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracie of <hi>Bigtan</hi> &amp; <hi>Teresh</hi> against <hi>Assue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> their soueraigne. The obseruations are: First, that God blessed him with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to detect it. Secondly, that it was made knowne to him when hee was vnlikelie to haue any such great intelligence, beeing then a person depressed by <hi>Haman.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that heauen is a watch tower euen for heathen Kings. Fourthlie, that <hi>Mordecai</hi> which ouerheard it sate without in the kings gate, and that the two conspirators kept the doore within, whereby aboue all expectation their whisperings came to his care, as he sate there like a forlorne person. Fiftly, that the treason being but then first conspired, and forthwith to bee executed
<pb facs="tcp:12281:40"/>when the king went next abroad, was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed before. Here was <hi>Mordecai</hi> a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of wings: hee informed <hi>Esther</hi> with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, as the prouidence of God had informed him by a diuine dispensation: so doth God haste to the succour of Kings. <hi>I know</hi> (saith the Church) <hi>that the Lord will helpe his annointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 20.6</note>
               <hi>and will heare him from his sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If there were euer nation, that had this truth sealed to their conscience by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration both of Gods <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell</hi> that is to say, both of his execution and intention to reueale conspiracies, it is this, in which the Lord hath excelled himselfe in miraculous mercies. Wee may truely translate <hi>Dauids</hi> wordes to our selues. <hi>If the Lord had not beene on our side</hi> (<hi>may</hi> England <hi>now saie</hi>) <hi>If the Lord had not beene on our side,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 124 1.2.3</note> when men <hi>rose vp against vs, they had then swallowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled against</hi> our Queene. How many conspirators are gone to their owne places, with their bloud vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:12281:41"/>their heads? How desperate, how se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, and how neerely and immnently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced haue their attempts beene? so that the conspirators which remaine vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced or vnconuerted by such a strer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out hand of God, are more wicked then wickednes it selfe. And I trust when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they conspire, they shall find in their confusion, that the hand of God is stretched forth still.</p>
            <p>Beloued, I haue not beene moued to this or any other course by any, and I do well vnderstand vnder what penaltie wee go which preach the word, if we seeke not to glorifie God in our ministerie. I doe very humblie beseech you therefore to ioine your godlie care or looking deepely into this matter, to the pensiue regarde which I haue had to propound it profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie vnto you. I say looke deepely into it, if euer you looked deeply into any thing. I speake to all Christian English hearts (for English is essentiall to Christian in this matter.) Brethren what will you do? will
<pb facs="tcp:12281:41"/>you not be a meanes by your cheerefull &amp; kind affection to your prince to reioice hit heart, and so to prolong hir life, when your duety and Gods glorie do both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist therein? To entertaine a Prince with heauines and silence which hath entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; saluted vs with so many good turns, is not laudable. The vnkindnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is inough to cut the heart of a prince. And concerning those principall ministers of state, whom her Maiestie hath put in place and holdeth in grace, shall they not bee vouchsafed the same in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences? If you keepe a court of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science within you, know that none are properly clients which owe suite to that Court, but your owne selues. It is neither wisedome nor godlines for men to make their friendes their foes. Lay no imputa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion vpon me of carnall counsell. By cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dutiful affection to those which may do you good in your good desires, you shall win them to do you good according to their meanes. And as for those great
<pb facs="tcp:12281:42"/>persons themselues, as I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that no man present hath ought to saie, that will auoid the pointes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our dutie to them, which I haue vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (so it bee spoken vnder competent tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) so those more graue and sufficient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons either present or absent, as they shall by due calling haue accesse vnto them (as I haue hither) shall do well to trauell seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously with them to conteine them within the boundes of loue euen to their mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gners, and not to set their wits against the witte of the simple, or of the distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered. I know they will informe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of their dutie: but God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted exhortations to encounter temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I would there were an vniuersall loue daie in respect of all subiects. I would in respect of the prince that there were as it were an altar of consent built, and that all Gods and Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> vnreclaima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies were sacrificed vpon it by consent.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let vs applie our selues to
<pb facs="tcp:12281:42"/>the grace of God to take benefit of that wee haue heard: and let vs take these two lessons with vs for the keeping of a good conscience.</p>
            <p>First, let vs gird close vnto vs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Gods loue, to reuerence our Prince in our inward hearts, I saie let vs gird it close to vs, as a girdle of trueth to gird in our affections at that verie time, when wee are tempted <hi>to leaue our place</hi> and to enter into discontentments, let vs, not consult with flesh and bloud apart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let vs know, that howsoeuer these dreames of misliking of princes for conscience sake come in at the Iuorie gate, yet they goe out at the Iron posterne, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the olde embleme of dreames, that is to say, that after men are once plunged in this sinne, the spirit of God forsaketh them, and they are in a mysterie of all vnconscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nablenes and miserie, and know not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they goe.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture it will be secretly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, that there were more conuenient
<pb facs="tcp:12281:43"/>points to haue beene spoken of by mo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this time then this.</p>
            <p>My answere is, that I haue followed my conscience in the choice of this argument, for most conuenient of all others at this time, to my vnderstanding, and that vpon my maturest deliberation.</p>
            <p>It may be it will be replied, that all is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faults of subiects, and neuer a word against any one fault of any magistrate, which may import suspition of tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</p>
            <p>My answere is, that for the reprouing of magistrats neither my intelligence serueth, nor my calling to this place, nor this place, nor this time, nor this text. And for there prouing of the faults which I haue repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, my knowledge serueth me, so doth this time, and these times, so doth this text.</p>
            <p>And as touching suspition of tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. Although I am much affected to my prince, and loth to offend any magistrate, whose fauour I may keepe with the fauour of God: yet God which is the Lord of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:12281:43"/>learning, gifts, and conscience, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that as I haue gathered these things not without labour both of head and heart; so I haue sought in the same both to keepe all good conscience, and to be a poore meanes to helpe my brethen, and countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the like, by chusing and handling this text thus.</p>
            <p>And giue me leaue to speake one thing of mine owne particular. That my ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (the successe whereof I preferre before my life) is like to be among the people, and not amongst magistrates. And therefore I would not wittingly alienate the people, and so the Lord, from me both at once by abusing his word or his children.</p>
            <p>I do therefore with a premeditate aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of men, put my selfe, and my doings, and yourselues, &amp; your thoughts vpon the grace and mercy of God in Iesus Christ, to whom with the father and the holy Ghost, be all honour &amp; glory now and euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:44"/>
            <p>1602.</p>
            <p>At London</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Peter Short,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on Bred-streete hill neere to the end of old Fish-streete, at the signe of the Starre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12281:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>